We're going to start by implementing
我们将对这个评分矩阵
Funk Singular Value Decomposition on this ratings matrix as users as the rows,
应用 Funk SVD
movies as the columns,
行表示用户 列表示电影
and then the values that are filled in here are
单元格里的值表示
the ratings that were given for that particular user-movie combo.
特定用户-电影组合的评分
To begin with, here's what our function will look like.
首先 函数是这样的
It'll take in our ratings matrix,
参数包括 ratings_mat
which is essentially just this part up here.
即暂时这一部分
For now, how many latent features we want,
还包括潜在特征的数量
what our learning rate should be,
学习速率
and then the number of iterations that we want to perform.
以及迭代次数
So, the number of users is basically the number of rows that we have.
用户数量等于行数
So, the number of movies is just going to be this.
电影数量等于这个
The number of ratings is going to basically be the product of those two things,
评分数量等于这两个的乘积
so we could do this.
我们本可以这么计算
Unfortunately, if we have missing values,
但是 如果缺少值的话
this won't actually work,
这么计算就不可行
so I'm going to use this.
我将使用这部分代码
So, this is a nice function that goes through and counts the number of non-zeros,
这个函数将查看非零数字并计数
and essentially this np.isnan is going to go through our matrix,
这个 np.isnan 将遍历矩阵
and keep track of whether there's a missing value or not.
并记录是否缺少值
Basically, we're going to just create our matrices filled with random values.
我们将创建一个用随机值填充的矩阵
So, if you remember from the earlier movie,
在之前的视频中
we have two matrices: a user matrix,
我们有两个矩阵 一个是用户矩阵
which has the dimensions are users as the rows,
它的行数是用户数量
and the number of latent features as the columns;
列数等于潜在特征的数量
and then a movie matrix,
另一个是电影矩阵
which is the number of latent features as
行数等于潜在特征的数量
the rows and the number of movies as the columns,
列数等于电影数量
and basically this user-matrix dot product with the movie matrix is going to give
用户矩阵与电影矩阵的点积
us the original user-movie matrix.
将等于原始的用户-电影矩阵
So, for iteration in range iters,
for iteration in range(iters)
where iters, remember, is this thing that gets passed.
iters 是在这里传入的值
So, this is how many times we're going to go
表示我们将遍历矩阵对
through the pair of matrices and update the values.
并更新值多少次
So, what you saw in the movie is actually not even a full iteration,
在视频中看到的不是一次完整的迭代
and iteration is to do that,
一次完整的迭代
iteration process on every single value once.
需要遍历每个值一次
So, in this case,
现在
what we're saying is, we're going to do that 100 times.
我们将迭代 100 次
For each user-movie pair,
对于每个用户-电影对
so I'm going to say, "For each user."
对于每个用户
So, for every i in range n_users,
for i in range(n_users)
and then for every movie,
然后对于每部电影
so for every j in range n_movies.
for j in range(n_movies)
So, for every user-movie pair,
对于每个用户-电影对
what we want to do is if there's a rating,
如果有评分
so if there's a rating in the matrix,
如果矩阵中有评分
and that it's not null.
即不为空
In our case, our ratings are from 1-10.
我们的评分范围是 1-10
So I'm just going to say, "If they're greater than 0," and if we do something
所以如果评分大于 0
like np.nan greater than one or greater than 0,
如果 np.nan 大于 1 或大于 0
and you can see that that comes back as false.
结果为 false
So, that's a positive for us because basically
对我们来说是肯定的结果
we just want this to evaluate as false if it's a nan,
如果是 NaN 我们希望结果为 false
and true if there's actually a value that exists in there.
如果存在一个值 则为 true
So, here comes the actual iteration process that we saw in the video.
接下来是视频中演示的实际迭代过程
So, essentially, what we want to do is we want to calculate the
我们将计算
residual or the difference between the actual value,
实际值与
and what we have given the dot product from our matrices.
矩阵点积结果之间的差异
So, the actual value is this,
实际值是这个
and the value that we predict based on our matrix is
根据矩阵预测的值是
the ith row in the left matrix or the user matrix,
左侧矩阵（用户矩阵）的第 i 行
and the jth column in the V matrix or the movie Matrix.
以及 V 矩阵（电影矩阵）的第 j 列
So, our prediction is user_mat,
预测值等于 user_mat[]...
and we want the ith row.
我们想要第 i 行
So, the ith row and all of the columns,
所以是第 i 行和所有的列
and we want that dot product with the movie matrix,
与电影矩阵的点积
and that's going to get all of the rows,
这样会获得所有的行
but we just want the jth column.
但是我们只想第 j 列
Then, here, we're going to keep track of the total squared differences,
我们将在这里跟踪平方差之和
and this is just going to be useful in the case that we
如果我们希望每次迭代效果都更好
want to make sure that we're doing better with each iteration.
这部分代码将很有用
We can take a look at that sums of squares of our differences.
我们可以查看差值的平方和
So, in the updating process,
在更新流程中
we saw that basically what we want to do is go through
我们将查看该行的每项
each item in that row and each item in that column.
以及该列的每项
So, each item in the row of the user matrix and
即用户矩阵行中的每项
each item in the column of the movie matrix,
和电影矩阵列中的每项
and update those values according to the gradient,
然后根据梯度更新这些值
and we saw that the gradient is essentially equal to, so if we look at this.
梯度等于...
So, we saw that we could get that individual value as basically the original value.
原始值加上
So, I'm going to use a plus equal to,
我将使用 +=
say the old value,
即原始值
plus the learning rate times 2 times the difference,
加上学习速率乘以两倍的差值
times the value in the opposite matrix in the same spot.
再乘以对立矩阵中相同位置的值
If you look at the formula for the gradient before,
查看之前的梯度公式
you'll see that it was,
会发现...
I want to take the old value.
用原始值...
So, we could easily write this as user matrix i,
可以将这个公式写成
k equals the original user matrix i,
user_mat[i, k] 等于原始的
k plus the learning rate times 2 times the difference,
user_mat[i, k] 加上学习速率乘以两倍的差值
which we calculated up here,
我们在这里计算了差值
times the movie matrix,
再乘以对立矩阵（电影矩阵）中
the opposite matrix in the same position.
相同位置的值
Basically, updating the movie matrix looks very similar to this,
电影矩阵的更新公式很像
but in order to update this,
但是
what we want is the kth spot.
我们需要的是第 k 个位置
We're updating the k, j spot,
更新的是 [k, j] 位置
and we're doing it by the learning rate 2 times,
加上学习速率乘以两倍的...
and then this needs to be the location in the user matrix.
这里必须是用户矩阵中的位置
So, this is going to be the i, kth.
这个将是 [i, k]
So, that's basically our update,
这就是更新流程
and then at the end,
最后
I'm just going to write it in a print statement.
我将写一个输出语句
This needs to have a
这里漏了 %
[inaudible] This should be
这里应该是 user
the user, the opposite matrix.
即对立矩阵
So, this should be the user matrix not the movie matrix.
这个应该是用户矩阵 而不是电影矩阵
Oops, I saw see instead of sse.
抱歉 我看到了 see 而不是 sse
That should be sum squared.
这个应该是 sum squared 的简写
I found the bug.
我找到 bug 了
So, up here, this movie matrix should be
这个电影矩阵应该是
the number of latent features by the number of movies.
潜在特征的数量 x 电影数量
Great. So, this first line should be a bunch of 10s,
Great第一行应该是好几个 10
and as you can see here, it's pretty close.
可以看出很接近了
Then, this should be 8, 9, 10, 5,
这行应该是 8 9 10 5
and you can see we're a little farther away, and so on and so forth.
看起来差别有点大 等等
So, you can see it hasn't quite converged with
如果使用 4 个潜在特征并且仅迭代 10 次
only 10 iterations using four latent features,
收敛效果将不太好
but we can try it again.
可以再试一遍
So, if we use that same function.
使用相同的函数
When instead of 10 iterations, let's do 250.
但是迭代 250 次 而不是 10 次
So, what they ask us to do,
这里要求迭代 250 次
and so that's still pretty fast,
运行速度依然很快
but you can see that we get down to an error of essentially zero.
但是到后面出错了 有很多 0
So, if we look at our predictions versus the actual values now,
现在看看预测值与实际值
we're basically the same.
它们基本一样
There's just decimal differences here.
只是一些小数差别
Now, the next part is that we want to place a nan value in that ratings matrix.
下一步我们将在评分矩阵中添加一个 NaN 值
So, here, I've just placed a nan in the first part,
我在第一部分添加了一个 NaN
and we want to see if we can still compute things.
我们想看看是否依然能这么计算
So, what we know about what we did with
之前使用内置的函数
singular value decomposition earlier using the built-in was that,
计算奇异值分解结果时
it broke when we put a nan in.
如果放入 NaN 值 代码将崩溃
If we do this,
现在同样放入 NaN
so let's say we do 250 iterations.
迭代 250 次
You can see that it ran. It didn't break.
代码能运行没有崩溃
It converged really well,
收敛效果很好
and you can see that it even predicted 10.64.
甚至针对 NaN 所在的位置
So, it was a nan, but we know that there was
预测出 10.64 分
actually a 110 in that spot where we plugged in the nan.
实际上原来就是一个 10 分
So, not only did we get
代码不仅能够
a prediction that was pretty close to what we know the actual value was,
预测出与实际值很接近的值
we shoved the nan into the matrix,
而且当我们向矩阵中添加了 NaN 后
and it didn't break.
代码没有崩溃
So, there's just good things happening here all the way around.
所以我们的实现流程没有问题